This lesson concerns
exponential and logarithm functions.
In this first video, we'll be interested
in some properties.
Then we'll see an example of compared growths
and finally some examples of equations and inequations.
Concerning properties,
here are some propositions.
You have to find those which are true,
and those which are false.
The first one is the following:
for all real numbers a and b,
exp of a+b equals this big square root.
This proposition is true.
To justify this, you can simplify
the right hand side, recalling
properties of powers.
For example, if x is exp of 2a
and y is exp of 2b,
we recall that the square root
of x squared times y squared
is actually the same as
x squared times y squared,
all of this to the power 1/2.
With power properties,
we can say that it is the same as
x squared to the 1/2
times y squared to the 1/2
the squared followed by 1/2
can be simplified as 2 times 1/2.
We get x to the power of 2 times 1/2,
that is x,
times y to the power of 2 times 1/2, that is y.
This quantity over here
equals exp of a times exp of b,
namely exp of a + b.
It is true.
Second proposition:
for any real numbers a and b,
we have this equality.
Here the relation is false.
To prove that a relation is false,
it is enough to give a counter-example.
In other words, it is enough to find
a real number a and a real number b,
for which the relation isn't true.
There is many examples.
We can take a equals 1 and b equals -1.
When we replace into it,
we get 2 times exp of 0, that is 2.
And on the right hand side,
we get exp of 2 + exp of -2.
The value of exp of 2
is approximately 7.39.
You add exp of -2.
Its value doesn't matter because
it is a positive number.
So we have 7.39 + something of positive
has to be equal to 2.
It's impossible: there is a contradiction.
So the proposition is false.
Third example:
there exists
a real number a and a real number b,
which satisfy the same relation as above.
What has changed is
for any to there exists.
Can we find two real numbers which satisfy that?
Now, the answer is yes.
It is enough to take for example
a equals 0, and b equals 0.
On the left hand side,
we get 2 times exp of 0, that is 2,
has to be equal to
exp of 0, that is 1, plus exp of 0, that is 1,
and the result is also 2.
This proposition is true.
Last proposition:
there exists a real number a and a real number b
such that the inequality holds.
This one is a little bit more tricky.
The answer is no:
they don't exist,
this inequality is never true.
Notice that the following inequality always holds:
(exp of a minus exp of b) squared is non-negative.
And we can develop it,
so we get exp of 2 a
minus 2 times exp of a exp of b
plus exp of 2b,
has to be a non-negative number.
Then we can move
2 exp of a exp of b
to the other side.
We get the reverse of the previous
inequality, for any value of a and b.
This last inequality is false.