In this video we're going to see
an example of use of Euler's and de Moivre's formula.
We know to linearize cosine to the third of x.
To linearize means to rewrite
this quantity like
a function of trigonometric functions,
without power (2 ou 3 ...).
For this we need 3 tools.
The first one is Euler's formula (for cosine)
recalled over there.
The second one is de Moivre's formula,
we'll need the power 3,
because we have the power 3 at the beginning.
At last, the third tool
is the development
thanks to the Binomial's formula
(a+b)^3 = ...
The power 3 is
because we have the power 3 at the beginning.
How can we proceed ?
The first thing to do is to replace
the cosine by exponential
(thanks to Euler's formula).
The number below
can be put outside
and we get 1/2 to the third,
that is 1/8.
Let's now focus on the parentheses over here.
We have to develop something like (a+b)^3:
here we use the Binomial's formula.
This formula provides us
this development.
Here is the a to the third
+ 3 a squared times b
+3 a times b squared + b to the third.
Now we have to simplify
these expressions ...
... using de Moivre's formula.
This formula says that the powers can be written
inside the exponential.
After simplification,
we get this expression.
Once we've done this simplification,
there is one last step:
to use Euler's formula in reserve
namely to take the same exponentials
to form trigonometric functions.
For example, exp(i 3x) and exp(-i 3x)
gather together to a cosine.
In the same way, exp(i x) and exp(-i x)
gather together to a cosine too.
Therefore,
using the reverse of Euler's formula,
we see that the sum of exp(i 3x) and exp(-i 3x)
equals 2 times cosine of 3x.
The sum of exp(i x) and exp(-i x)
equals 2 times cosine of x
(up to the factor 3).
After simplification
we get the following expression.
Finally, cosine to the third of x
equals 1/4 times cosine of 3x + 3/4 times cosine of x.
We've linearized cosine to the third
because in the last expression, there isn't any more power.