This chapter concerns complex numbers.
We're going to see in this first video
different forms of some complex number,
then we'll give some symmetry properties
for some complex number.
In the third video,
we'll see an application of
Euler's and Moivre's formula.
There exists 2 main forms
of a complex number:
the standard form
and the exponential form.
How to pass from standard form to exponential form?
Here is a complex number in standard form,
with 1 as its real part,
and -sqrt(3) its imaginary part.
How can you find the exponential form?
For this, you have to compute
two things:
the radius r, which actually is the modulus of z,
and then the argument of z.
We always begin to compute r,
which
is actually the modulus of z:
we have an explicit formula that tells us
the modulus is the square root of
the real part squared, that is 1 squared +
the imaginary part squared,
that is the square root of 3 squared.
It comes 2.
Once we have the modulus r,
we can compute the argument of z.
It's called theta.
The argument must satisfy two things:
its cosine equals the real part of z
divided by its modulus (1/2),
its sinus equals the imaginary part of z
again divided by its modulus.
It comes a equations system,
which admits only 1 solution
up to 2kPi.
Generally, you can take the solution
either between 0 and 2Pi
or between -Pi and Pi. (there is no preference)
Here the solution is -Pi/3 (or -Pi/3+2Pi):
there is a choice to do.
Once you have found the angle theta
(or the argument of z)
We know how to write the complex number
in the trigonometric form
(which is the modulus multiplied by
cosine of the argument + i times sinus of the argument)
and its exponential form is:
the modulus multiplied by exp(i times argument).
It's easier to change the exponential form
into the standard form.
Here is a complex number in standard form.
It's straightforward to identify
the modulus: it's the square root of 2
and the angle (the argument):
here is Pi/4.
From this, we find the standard form:
z equals
its modulus (sqrt(2)) multiplied by
cosine of the argument (cos(Pi/4))
+ i times its modulus (again)
multiplied by sinus of the argument.
We know the correspondant usual values
and we get for both sqrt(2)/2,
and after simplification
we get the standard form of z: 1+i.