Now let's be interested in some of properties
of complex numbers.
Concerning geometric symmetries,
Let me recall the exponential form:
if z is r exp(i theta)
then r is the modulus of z,
and theta is the argument of z.
We know that the conjugate of z
equals r exp(-i theta).
Therefore we can see that z and the conjugate of z
have the same modulus, the same radius.
However the argument of the conjugate of z
equals the opposite of the argument of z.
Then for negative z,
negative z can be written like that,
but we know that -1 equals exp( i Pi).
Therefore the exponential form of -z
is equal to that.
And again we can see that
the modulus of -z is equal to the modulus of z,
but the argument of -z
is equal to arg(z) to which you have to add Pi.
Geometrically,
here we've put a point M in the plane R^2.
This point M also represents a complex number,
called the affix of M over here.
If you take the symmetric point,
with respect to the x-acis, then
the affix of M'
is exactly equal to
the conjugate of the affix of M.
Namely z' = the conjugate of z.
Now if you take the symmetric point
with respect to the origin,
of M, then its affix
equals -z.
From z, we've drawn the conjugate of z
the both numbers have the same modulus,
in contrast with the argument which are opposite.
Then, for z'' namely -z
we also have the same modulus,
however
the relation between the two angles,
is the angle theta over here
to which you add Pi
to get the angle of M''.
That's it for the symmetries.
Now let's focus on
the simplification of two complex numbers.
This is a very common trick:
you can simplify 2-i over 1+3i
in other words,
to give the standard form of this complex number.
How to do that?
There's a way which always works:
you have to multiply above and below
by the conjugate
of the complex number below.
Here you have to multiply by 1-3i
(which is the conjugate of 1+3i).
Indeed we know that
z times the conjugate of z equals
the modulus of z squared.
Here the value is 10.
Above, after simplification,
we get -1-7i.
Then we separe real and imaginary parts
to get the standard form of the complex number
like this.