In this video, we're going to give a relationship
between the sign of the derivative of some function
and the variations of the function.
Then we're going to talk geometrically
about the existence of local extrema.
Here is a green function f,
it's f(x) = sin(x/2).
We've put a point A on the graph.
We've drawn the orange tangent line
to the graph at this point A.
Recall that the slope of the tangent line is precisely
the derivative of f taken at this point.
For instance, the slope of this tangent line
is f ' of zero.
Because the tangent line
is an increasing function
we know that its slope is a positive number,
therefore f '(0) is a positive number.
I'm going to move the point A,
the tangent line is progressively changing.
During this, we're going to represent
the values of f '(x),
in other words the values of the slope of the tangent line.
We've already said that is the slope is a positive number.
Progressively, my tangent line is changing a little bit,
but the slopes are still positive numbers.
There are represented in violet.
I keep going to move
and there exists a moment where the tangent line
becomes a horizontal line.
This a critical point:
precisely when my tangent line becomes
a horizontal line
the slope vanishes,
namely f '(x) equals 0.
If I continue to move the point A,
then the tangent line
is becoming a decreasing function.
In other words its slope is becoming a negative number.
It impacts the sign of the derivative of f.
From this,
there is a first thing
we can say:
f is an increasing function (until over here)
if and only if f '(x) is a positive number.
Then f is becoming a decreasing function (until over here)
if and only if f '(x) is a negative number.
This is the first fact we can say.
The second fact:
If I come back to the critical point,
Just before this critical point
where the tangent line is a horizontal line,
we have f '(x) is a positive number.
Then f '(x) vanishes and
becomes a negative number.
In other words, f '(x) has its sign which changes
(from positive to negative).
This means that f
admits a local extremum at this point
exactly where the derivative vanishes.
(the derivative vanishes at this point)
There are 2 kind of extrema:
minimum and maximum.
The nature can be determined geometrically.
Here it turns out that it's a maximum,
called a local maximum:
we know what is happening around A
but earlier or later the function could be
greater than this value.
We have the same fact in this side.
The derivative vanishes,
a little bit before it is a negative number,
a little bit after it is a positive number.
Therefore we have an extremum:
it turns out that it is a minimum.
And the important fact
is that there is no extremum elsewhere.
If the derivative doesn't vanishe then
we know that f doesn't admit neither minimum nor maximum.