Most of functions we meet
depend on not only one but on many variables.
You have to know how to compute the derivative
of some function, depending on many variables,
with respect to one of the given variable.
We're going to see this through 2 examples.
Let's look this first function f.
It depends on t and x.
The x over here is the variable against which
we have to take the derivative of f.
Therefore the only variable which matters here is x.
And all the other variables are considered as a parameter,
in other words as a constant.
How to take the derivative of f with respect to x?
In red is what is depending on x.
The rest of it is a constant.
Taking the derivative of f w.r.t x,
we have to take the derivative of exp(x)
(the t in front of it is a constant)
The constant t stays in the same place.
It's similar for the t squared.
The derivative of f w.r.t. x is then
t times exp(x)
(because the derivative of exp(x) is exp(x))
plus a constant times x
which becomes the constant:
that is t squared.
Now we're interested in the same function
and we would like to take the derivative of it
with respect to t.
This time roles are exchanged:
what isn't t is considered as a constant.
Hence exp(x) is a constant
and the derivative of t times exp(x)
is the constant exp(x).
And the derivative of t squared times x,
it comes 2 t times the constant.
Notice that for the same function,
the derivatives are not the same according to
the choice of the variable.
At last, with the same expression,
let's consider a third function
depending on the variable a.
Because the function is depending on a
and a is not explicit in the expression,
all of this is considered as a constant
(w.r.t. a)
and taking the derivative of h w.r.t. a
is taking the derivative of a constant,
so the result is 0.
Here is a second and little more tricky example.
One more time, we have an expression
which depend on t and x.
We would like to take the derivative w.r.t. x.
In red is what depends on x,
the rest of it doesn't depend on x
and is considered as a constant.
Hence cos(t^2) is a constant here
as well as the square root of t.
Both will appear in the derivative.
Now we have to take the derivative of ln(x) squared.
ln(x) squared has the form u squared.
The derivative of u squared
equals 2 u times u'.
We get 2 ln(x) times the derivative of ln(x),
which is 1 over x.
The constant is multiplied by
2 u (2 ln(x) ) times u' (1/x).
+ the derivative of some constant times 1 / x:
the constant is the same and the derivative of 1/x
is - 1/x squared.
This can be written as the following.
(it's not an obligation)
Now we take the derivative of the same function
but this time depending on t.
This time roles are exchanged:
what isn't depending on t is considered as a constant.
Hence ln(x)^2 is a constant,
as well as 1 over x.
We have to take the derivative of cos(t^2),
namely cos(u).
The derivative of cos(u)
is - sin(u) times u'.
Here u is t squared,
u' is then 2t.
Then we get something like that:
- sin(u) times u' times the constant
+ the constant 1/x
times the derivative of square root of t,
which is 1 over 2 square root of .
All of this can be written like that.