In this course,
we're going to talk about derivative functions.
In this first video, we'll be interested in tangent lines.
For that, we need the concept of derivative number.
Then we'll give
the general tangent line equation.
On the picture, we've drawn
in green the graphe of some function
(here is the sinus function),
on which we've put a first point A.
And we have in red the tangent line to the graph
of f that passes through the point A.
The tangent line is the best line
which approches the green graph to A.
We've put a second point B,
right here over the graph.
Finally we've drawn the blue line
which passes through A and B.
The first question you can ask is:
what is the slope of the blue line?
It's well-known:
the slope of the blue line
is the slope between A and B.
And the value is well-known:
f(b) minus f(a) all over b minus a.
Now, let's move
the point B to the point A.
If we do this, we notice
that the blue line
is coming closer
of the red line, which is the tangent line.
Taking the limit,
both of lines are superposed.
It means
that we can find
the slope of the red tangent line.
Actually, because B comes closer to A,
the slope of the tangent line simply is
the limit when b tends to a
of the slope between A and B.
This limit has a name:
the derivative number of
the function f at a.
It has a name but also a notation:
it's denoted by f '(a).
All of this gives us the slope of the tangent line,
but the complete tangent line equation is missing.
The complete tangent line equation
can be easily found:
this is the one over here:
the tangent line equation
to the graph of f at a.
Let's do some computation.
Let f be the sinus function.
We want to determine
the tangent line equation to f at (0,0).
To this aim,
I need to compute the derivative.
The derivative of sinus is cosine.
Then I take the derivative at 0, and I get 1.
The 1 over here
is actually the slope of the tangent line.
Now I can find the other part of the equation.
I deduce that the tangent line
to the graph of f at (0,0)
(f(0) equals 0)
has its equation:
y equals 1 times (x minus 0) plus f(0)
namely y equals x.