This first lesson is about trigonometry
We're going to talk about 3 topics:
the first one concerns trigonometric functions
We'll talk about addition formula,
which are the most important formula
at last,
we'll show how to solve a trigonometric equation
Concerning trigonometric functions,
we have represented here
what we call the trigonometric circle.
This circle
is the circle with center O, the origin,
and with 1 as radius.
On the circle,
we've put an angle, alpha,
in violet,
and this angle determines a point on the circle.
This point admits coordinates.
Its coordinates
are depending on the angle alpha.
And its coordinates are precisely the so-called trigonometric functions, namely on the x-axis, the length over there
we define what we call the cosine of alpha
and on the y-axis,
we define what we call the sinus of alpha.
We can define ...
a third trigonometric function: drawing the half-line over there,
and drawing the vertical line passing through the point (1,0).
If we take the intersection of these two straight lines
then the height in green over there
also depends on alpha.
Because if I move alpha
then the height is moving too,
and this height is called the tangent of alpha.
So we can see a very important property,
which relies the three trigonometric functions :
thanks to Thales' theorem.
Indeed here you have a triangle
and inside of it, you can find
this segment over there
and this one, which are parallel.
Thales' theorem says that the quotient between
the length of this segment and the lenght of this one is equal to the quotient between the length of the segment over there
and the one over there.
Namely,
sinus of alpha
divided by tangent of alpha is equal to cosine of alpha divided by the length of the large segment which is 1.
This can be rewritten,
this is the well-known formula, as tangent of alpha equals sinus of alpha over cosine of alpha.
This is a first and very useful property. A second property
comes from
the little triangle over here.
This little triangle has a 90 degrees-angle.
In this kind of triangle,
we can apply the Pythagoras' Theorem.
It says that
the sum of the length squared
here and here is equal to the length squared of the larger segment. Its length equals 1
whatever the value
of alpha.
So Pythagoras' Theorem says: the length over here, sinus of x ...
... squared plus the length over here,
cosine of x squared, is equal to 1 squared.
Finally, we can recall usual values.
We put the usual values:
Pi/6, Pi/4, Pi/3.
You absolutely need to know
the cosine values of these usual values
and the sinus values too.
Once we know the usual values,
how to compute other values such that sinus of -Pi/3 ?
We're going to see some symmetry properties.
We have the trigonometric circle with an angle, called x.
Now we're looking the angle -x.
It's going to the other side.
We're looking for its coordinates.
Its coordinates:
on the x-axis, one can see that the cosine of -x,
the length over here, is exactly the same as
the cosine of x.
So we get a first property:
cosine of -x equals cosine of x.
By contrast, the sinus of -x,
the y-coordinate here,
is the same length as the sinus of x,
but with a negative sign in front of.
So sinus of -x equals - sinus of x.
This can be used to determine
this kind of value.
For example, what is the value of sinus of -Pi/3 ?
sinus of -Pi/3 is actually - sinus of Pi/3,
namely - the square root of 3 over 2.
Now,
how to compute the cosine of 2Pi/3 ?
Again we need
some other symmetry properties.
For example, with x given, we can draw
the angle x + Pi/2:
I take x and turn of one quarter.
We get the green angle over there.
We're looking for the coordinates of this angle.
The height over here,
I can draw it,
I can see that the sinus of x+Pi/2 has actually the same value as
the cosine of x.
We get a first relation:
sinus of x+Pi/2 equals cosine of x.
This time, I'm interested in
its x-coordinate.
I can see that the cosine of x+Pi/2
has exactly the same length as the sinus of x, but with a negative sign in front of it (because we are on the negative side over the x-axis).
We get the formula: cosine of x+Pi/2
equals - sinus of x.
It is useful to compute this value.
Indeed 2Pi/3 ...
can be rewritten as the sum of two angles: Pi/6 + Pi/2.
And we know that the cosine of x
+Pi/2 is equal to - sinus of x, namely -sinus of Pi/6,
and we finally get a well-known usual value.
We know that sinus of Pi/6 is equal to one half.