Welcome in this preparation of the examination entrance
of the EPF Graduate School of Engineering
My name is Jeremy Rouot and I am a mathematics teacher at EPF
and I will accompany you during this preparation
In this video, I will present you the contents of this formation
with the different courses and the Moodle platform,
due to which we will communicate all together,
to access of the different pdf files and video files of the courses,
and also to provide you some tests to see if you reached the requirements of the lessons
Let's begin to access this platform:
type the address http://moodle.epf.fr/
you reach this page where you can put
your id and your password, which were given to you
After logging in, you get a series of courses and you should see the course
"SPOC Concours EPF"  You click on this link
I will switch on the student mode so that you will see the same page as me
Here on the course's page, you can change the language to english
You have a first link to download a presentation's video of EPF Troyes,
which was made by Chinese students at EPF
Click on the link to download the zip archive on your computer
and extract it to have the video file
Then I let you enjoy this video
You have one link where you will be able to introduce yourself
You can create a new discussion: for instance I introduced myself here
that is, I am Jérémy Rouot, math teacher at EPF
My hobby is bikes and I give you a QR code to add me on WeChat
I invite you to create a discussion to speak a bit about yourself here
You can either ask to me your question on WeChat or if you want to share your question
You can post a topic to present your problem that you encountered
Let's come back on the main page of the course
You have a first section about how to answer questions of this preparation
Indeed there will be tests and you will be told to respect a syntax so that your answers can be correct
We will come back to it after
This second section is the first chapter of the preparation and concerns Trigonometry
Each course is organized as follows: you have the competencies that you should get at the end of this chapter
You have links to download the pdf file of the course about Trigonometry
and to download videos related to this lesson
As before, you have to download the zip archive on your computer
and to extract it to have access to the videos of the course
Once you finished to work on the pdf file and the video files
You can train yourself with several tests
You can do these tests as many of times as you want  You won't have marked on these tests
At each different attempts, questions are not the same, so do not hesitate to do tests several times
For instance, I entered in this test and I selected one question
This test has 15 questions, and in the twelfth question I am told to expand the expression
(sine of minus 5 times r minus pi) in terms of (sine of 5 times r) or (cosine of 5 times r)
The answer to this question is (sine of 5 times r)
How to enter correctly (sine of 5 times r)?
To help you, this "Sheet summary"'s file contains different mathematical expressions
and the corresponding expressions to enter in Moodle
For instance, for the sine function, to enter sine of 2 times pi times beta,
You must enter (sine of 2 times "p" "i" and "b" "e" "t" "a")
Indeed the pi number is indicated here as "p" "i" and the Greek letter beta is entered as "b" "e" "t" "a"
Finally the sine function can be entered as "s" "i" "n" "bracket"
and you enter the input in the brackets  Here the input of the sine function is 5 times r
I enter "5" "asterisk" because "asterisk" is the multiplication symbol
Below your answer box is displayed the mathematical expression corresponding to what you entered
Namely, if you forgot a bracket, one indicates that your answer is not valid
Indeed it specifies to add a closing bracket
Careful, this displayed expression may be not correct  It is just an interpretation of what you entered and it could be incorrect
If I add "plus" "1", it would have displayed the corresponding expression
Then you can pass to the next question to reach a new question
In this question you have to choose the correct answer among four potential answers
You can go back to the previous question if you want to modify it
To validate all your answers, you click here "Finish attempt"
and you can send all your answers to the system and you get a summary of your test
I did not answer to the first question and it yields the right mathematical answer and the right syntax to enter it
For instance (minus square root of three over 2), from this file
the square root function should be entered as "s" "q" "r" "t" and the input is inside  brackets
To get used to with this syntax, I strongly advice you to have a look at the first section,
which will train you to answer correctly to the questions
The first link gives you instructions on this syntax to answer correctly to the questions
The number pi can be entered as "p" "i" or with a percentage symbol "%" in front
The multiplication symbol is the "asterisk", the power function, the brackets
as soon as you have a rational expression, you should not forget brackets
You can read this page and if you encounter mathematical object that you don't understand such as matrices, you can skip it
The second link refers to a quiz, which is not evaluated  You can do it several times because most questions are random
And this quiz is the perfect exercise to get used to with the specific syntax to enter mathematical expressions
Keep this "Sheet summary" next to you as soon as you are answering questions on Moodle
This point concerns Greek letters, to enter the Greek letter "alpha" you must type "a" "l" "p" "h" "a"
Concerning the test of the first section, the first part is informative
To enter "x" at the power minus 2, you have to enter "x" "hat" "bracket" "-2" "bracket"
In question 1, you are told to enter the expression corresponding to "y" equals to "3" times "x" plus "5"
So I enter "y" "=" "3" "*" "+" "5"
Below the answer box, your answer is interpretated and displayed with mathematical symbols
Once you are satisfied, you may pass on the next question  We skip the question 2
The third question concerns Greek letters  Here you have to enter the expression
"alpha" times exponential of "pi" times "x"
"alpha" is a Greek letter and you may refer here or to your sheet summary
To enter the letter "alpha" you have to type "a" "l" "p" "h" "a"
Let's enter it  "a" "l" "p" "h" "a" "*" exponential of pi times x
The exponential function can be entered as "e" "x" "p" and the input is between brackets
So "e" "x" "p" and in brackets we put "pi" times "x"
Likewise "pi" can be entered as "p" "i"  So "p" "i" "*" "x" and I close the brackets
Once you finished you get an interpretation of what you entered and if you forgot a bracket, it will tell you
Once again, the displayed expression here corresponds to what you entered in the answer box and may be not the correct answer
You may have added "x" at the power "2" and it doesn't tell you if it's right or wrong
Then you can jump to the following questions
Train yourself on this quiz and keep this sheet summary next to you!
This presentation is about to finish
If you have any question (mathematical or concerning Moodle or how to answer questions),
Please do not hesitate to send me a message either on Moodle or via WeChat
I wish you all the best for this week and I am looking forward to seeing you at EPF!