In this video, we're going to show
how to solve an equation which involves ln.
and then an example
of a resolution of some inequation which involves exp.
In the first example,
we're looking to solve this equation.
We proceed in two parts:
the first one is to determine the set of definition of this equation.
Because of the ln here
(which is a function well-defined on positive numbers)
what is inside of ln, has to be a positive number.
This equation provides us two constraints:
x has to be a positive number
and 1 over x has to be a positive number too.
These two constraints can be group together:
1/x > 0 is actually
equivalent to x >0.
So these two constraints are the same.
Together, it gives us x > 0.
This first part is very important.
Once it's done, we come back to the equation.
When it is possible,
we always
put the equation in the following form:
ln equals ln.
Then we can apply the exponential on both sides,
because we know that
exp of ln of a equals a.
It allows us to remove the ln().
That's what we do here,
we get this equation is equivalent to
x equals 1/x.
This equivalence is only true on
domain of definition given above.
You have to keep in mind that
x has to be a positive number.
We now focus on solving
this new equation.
To this aim, we can
multiply both sides by x.
We get x squared equals 1.
This equation
admits two real solutions: + or - 1.
But we remind that x is in the domain,
it has to be a positive number.
Finally there is only one solution.
In other words,
S equals 1.
For the second example,
we want to solve this inequation.
The variable here is phi.
In the same way,
the first part is to determine
the domain of definition of this inequation.
Because of the quotient,
exp of phi + 1 hasn't to be zero.
But exp of phi is always a positive number,
for any value of phi,
therefore this number isn't equal to zero.
This constraint isn't a true constraint.
It doesn't give us a constraint over phi.
Besides the exponential function is defined on R.
So phi can be any real number.
So phi belongs to R.
We have no restriction for this inequation.
Then, like previously,
because of the quotient here,
the idea is to multiply both sides
by exp of phi +1.
This doesn't change the sign of the inequality,
because exp of phi + 1 is a positive number.
Once we did this,
we group exp of phi together.
It gives us 1 exp of phi on the right hand side
and for the constant,
on the left hand side,
we get 1.
How to get the constraint on phi?
It is enough now
to take ln to both sides
of the inequality.
We can do that because
ln is an increasing function:
so the inequality doesn't change.
Therefore we get
ln of 1, that is 0,
has to be greater than ln of exp of phi,
that is phi.
Finally
the set of solutions of this inequation
is the set of phi which are negative numbers,
in other words, - infinity to 0.
The constraint here is respected.