During this video, we're going to see
how to compute limits in which exp and ln occur.
The first point is about
compared growths: they compare
exp, ln functions with respect to power functions.
Then we'll give another example
of computation of some limit.
Here are the graph of exp (in black)
and the graph of ln (in violet).
These functions are symmetric w.r.t to the line y=x.
Now we draw power functions.
In green is the function x to the power 1.06.
We can change the power:
while the power is increasing,
we notice that the green function
is approaching the graph of exp.
But when x tends to +infinity,
exponential function increases
more quickly than any power functions
(in +infinity)
This a property we can write:
the quotient of exp of x and power function x to alpha
tends to +infinity
when x tends to +infinity.
It means that the exponential function
is "stronger" than any power function.
Now
when power decreases,
in the same way, graphs of power functions
are approaching the graph of ln.
But
when x tends to +infinity,
for any power here,
logarithm function tends to +infinity
more slowly than power function.
In other words, we can translate
this property into a limit of quotient.
The quotient of ln of x over x to alpha,
for any alpha,
when x tends to +infinity,
is going to zero.
It means that ln is always "weaker" than
any power functions in +infinity.
That is a first use of these functions
for computation of some limits.
Second example:
how to compute this kind of limit?
The first thing you have to ask yourself is:
can you compute it without transformation?
We notice that in the first part,
it is the x squared which matters in +infinity,
so it goes to +infinity.
Because of the square root,
all of this tends to +infinity.
Here we have a "minus x",
which tends to - infinity.
Therefore we have the (undefined) form:
+ infinity - infinity
To compute this kind of limit,
we then have to transform the quantity.
So
this is a classical operation,
because we have a square root of something minus something
So we multiply this quantity inside ln by
its conjugate quantity.
The conjugate quantity of
sqrt a - sqrt b is
sqrt a + sqrt b.
To not change the value,
we have to multiply both above and below
by the same thing.
We multiply by
the square root of x squared + x -1
plus x.
Above we get a classical polynomial identity,
which is
(sqrt a - sqrt b) times (sqrt a + sqrt b)
is actually a - b.
Because of the squared,
we can remove the square root here.
And x becomes x squared.
We can simplify and we obtain this.
Once we have this form,
we can factor above and below
by the biggest power we can find.
Above the biggest power is x.
Below,
the biggest power inside the square root
is x squared.
After factor, we get his,
and now we put the x squared in front of the square root.
Keep in mind that square root of x squared
is the absolute value of x.
But here we're interested in the limit
when x tends to +infinity.
Hence x will be a positive number.
So in this case,
you can remove the absolute value.
At last, we can simplify all of these x.
We get
this quantity over here.
(after simplification)
Notice that the new quantity is easier than the first one.
Indeed,
it is easier to find the limit of this quantity:
when x tends to +infinity, above is going to 1,
and below,
we get 1 + square root of 1
(all of this tends to zero).
Then square root of 1 plus 1 is 2.
So the limit of ln of this quotient
is going to be ln of 1 over 2.
Thanks to the ln properties,
we get - ln of 2.