We're going to see how to solve trigonometric equations.
One knows very well how to solve equation:
cos()=cos()
We have a formula for this.
We also know how to solve equation:
sin()=sin(),
we have an other formula for this.
However we do not know how to solve directly
cos()=sin()
We'll see that we'll need one of the previous form.
Let's focus on this trigonometric equation.
To solve this trigonometric equation,
is to find
all the x values
for which the equality is true.
To solve this equation,
the first thing to do is to change
the value sqrt(2)/2,
into a cosine of something.
Here it is straightforward because
sqrt(2)/2 is actually equal to cos(Pi/4).
This first step is very important.
Once we had written it,
we get an equation cos()=cos().
And we have a formula
for solutions of this kind of equation.
The formula always has 2 parts as you can see.
Then we have,
2x equals Pi/4 to which we have to add 2kPi
or (and you have to keep in mind this "or")
2x equals minus the angle, namely -Pi/4 +2kPi.
Once you have this 2 parts,
you have to find x.
Here, you only need to divide by 2,
and be careful when you divide by 2,
Pi/4 becomes Pi/8,
but you also need to divide 2kPi by 2
which becomes kPi.
Hence we can write
the set of the solutions of this equation,
like this, with 2 parts:
the first one Pi/8+kP
and the second one
-Pi/8+kP (where k is an integer).
Notice there is an infinity of solutions.
Second example with sinus.
It's the same way as before.
The first thing to do is to change this value 1/2,
to a sinus of something.
It turns out that 1/2 is sin(Pi/6).
Once we have this form, we can apply
solutions formula for sinus,
which is also
in 2 parts.
The first part is the same as for cosine:
4x equals Pi/6+2kPi.
And the second one is a little bit different:
4x equals ...
... Pi minus the angle over here, that is Pi/6
to which we add 2kPi.
One more time, you have to find x.
Therefore you need to divide these equations by 4.
Pi/6 becomes Pi/24,
and do not forget to dived 2kPi by 4
which becomes 4Pi/2.
We obtain the set of solutions of the equation
right there,
with an integer k.
Finally, a last equation.
An equation of type cos()=sin().
We don't have an explicit formula to solve this.
So how can you do ?
We're going to use symetry formula
we've seen previously.
We can switch the sinus to a cosine,
(in this case, we'll get cos()=cos())
otherwise we can switch cosine to sinus
(in the latter case, we'll get sin()=sin()).
You have a choice to do.
I've chosen to switch the sinus to a cosine,
and we remind
of sin(x) equals cos(x-Pi/2).
Once we had rewritten the equation,
we can apply as before
the solutions formula for cosine.
It's in to 2 parts (keep in mind!).
Therefore 2x equals the angle x-Pi/2 +2kPi
or
2x equals negative the angle, that is
-x + Pi/2 + 2kPi.
At last, you have to find x.
You put all x together (on the left hand side)
and we get only one x
has to be equal to - Pi/2 +2kPi
or
3x has to be equal to Pi/2 +2kPi.
There's nothing to do with the first equation.
But for the second one, you have to divide by 3
and we get
(right here a - sign is missing)
and we get for this side
Pi/6+2kPi/3.
The set of solutions
(with a - sign right here)
is equal to that.