We're going to see addition formula and a straightforward application: duplication formula.
So the trigonometric addition formula
are the most important amongst all trigonometric formula.
The main reason is that from these formula,
we can deduce all the others.
Here we recall addition formula:
cosine of x+y and sinus of x+y,
which are available for all real x and y.
Be careful: cosine switch + sign to - sign
instead of sinus which keeps the same sign.
We immediately can deduce from them
the following formula, with a cosine of x minus y.
Actually we replace all of y by -y
and we get cosine of x cosine of - y minus sinus of x sinus -y.
Because cos(-x)=cos(x), this is the same
but sin(-y)=-sin(y), both - signs give together a + sign.
We get the formula over here for cos(x-y) with a +sign.
Conversely, sin(x-y), switching all the y by -y
we get in the same way: the -sign from the sinus
is going outside et the formula follows.
You absolutely have to remember these 2 (ou 4) formula.
A first application:
if you want to compute cos(x+Pi/3), we apply the formula,
the +sign becomes a -sign
and we remind of the usual values of cos(Pi/3) et sin(Pi/3).
Namely, cosine becomes 1/2
and sinus becomes the square root of 3 over 2.
An other and little more tricky example:
how to compute sinus of Pi/12 ?
Sin(Pi/12) is not an usual value.
But we can transform these quantity into two usual values,
if we notice that Pi/12 is actually equal to 4Pi/12 - 3Pi/12.
It turns out that 4Pi/12=Pi/3
which is an usual value. And 3Pi/12 = Pi/4
therefore we can apply addition formula for sinus,
which gives us this,
and all the values are well-known usual values.
The result follows.
We can simplify to obtain:
the square root of 6 minus the square root of 2, all of this over 4,
for the value of sin(Pi/12).
Obviously, we could compute in the same way cos(Pi/12).
So a first application of addition formula
is what we call duplication formula.
Namely, cosine of 2x is actually cosine of x+x,
and using the addition formula,
we get something like that:
cosine of x squared minus sinus of x squared.
From this, we remind of
the trigonometric Pythagoras' formula, in other words:
cos^2+sin^2=1.
Therefore we can switch
the one or the other one
the cos^2 or the sin^2
to 1-sin^2 or to 1-cos^2.
Here I switch cos^2 to 1-sin^2
and I get 1-2sin^2(x).
Otherwise, if I switch sin^2 to 1-cos^2,
then I get 2cos^2(x)-1.
These 3 green quantities are the same,
called duplication formula for cosine.
At last, duplication formula for sinus:
it is easier,
because we notice that we get 2 times cos(x)sin(x),
and here is the duplication formula for sinus.
So we can apply these duplication formula
in two different ways.
We're going to see this with the cosine.
Indeed, reversely,
cosine squared is equal to 1 ...
(if I put the 1 in the other side)
...+ cosine of 2x, all of that above 2.
For example: let's compute cosine of Pi/8.
Again Pi/8 isn't an usual value.
So we should go back to usual values.
Cos(Pi/8) is not directly computable,
but we can compute
cos(Pi/8)^2,
using the previous formula.
cos(Pi/8)^2 equals
cosine of 2 times Pi/8 (=Pi/4) +1
all of that over 2.
But we know the value of cos(Pi/4)
which is the square root of 2 over 2.
Hence cos(Pi/8)^2 is finally equal
to the square root of 2 +2, over 2.
The last thing to do is
to take the square root of these quantities.
Be careful,
the square root of a^2 is not a.
Actually the square root of a^2
is the absolute value of a.
It depends on whether
a is a positive or a negative number.
Here Pi/8 is between 0 and Pi/2,
therefore cos(Pi/8) is necessarly positive.
Hence the square root of cos(Pi/8)^2
is equal to cos(Pi/8).
It is the square root of all of that.