This lesson is about integrals and primitives.
We'll give the relation between these two objects.
In this first video, we're going to talk about integral,
to give a definition and some properties.
Then we're going to see how to compute
the integrale of some constant function.
Here is a graph of some positive function f.
It means the graph is above the x-axis.
We're interested in the area below the graph:
namely between the graph and the x-axis
delimited by two points:
a=1 and b=5.
That area, that quantity,
is denoted like this.
It depends on a and b
but also on the function f.
We read the number like:
the integral from a to b of f (x) dx.
It can be computed and here the value is 10.88.
For negative function,
we're interested in the area but this time
above the graph (between the graph and the x-axis).
That area is a positive number,
but the integral from a to b of f(x)
is going to be a negative number.
Actually the integral of a negative function
is the opposite of the value of the area.
Here it comes -10.88.
A first property:
Here is the graph of some positive function,
and we're looking to compute the area
between a and b of this function.
It is easy to figure out that
when we cut the interval a,b into two intervals a,c and c,b
the area below the graph
between a and b equals
the area between a and c + the area between c and b.
These two area in green and red can be denoted by
integrals:
here is the integral between a and c
and here is the integral between c and b.
If you compute a1+a1 (the areas),
then you get 10.35
And moving c
is going to change a1 and a2,
but the sum a1+a2 doesn't change.
This result is actually the integral
between a and b.
This relation is called
Chasles' relation.
The integral between a and b equals
the integral between a and c + the integral between c and b
whatever the point c.
Let's continue by
the computation of the integral of some constant.
It is very important and you have to know how to do it quickly.
The formula is the following:
the integral between a and b of c
is equal to b-a (the length of the intervall a,b)
multiplied by the constant c inside the integral.
Actually to compute the integral of some constant
(because a constant function is a horizontal line)
the area below the line is the area of a rectangle.
Area of a rectangle is well-known:
the base (here is b-a that is 5-1)
times the height
(here is the value of the constant minus 0, that is c)
At last, the integral of a constant c between 1 and 5,
is equal to 5-1 times the height c.