In this video, we're going to see
the notion of primitives.
At the beginning, we'll give some examples
of computation of primitives.
Then we'll show the relation with computation of integrals.
A primitive of some function f
is an other function F
such that if you take the derivative of F
then you get f.
For instance,
looking for a primitive of f(x)=2x
is looking for a function F,
such that the derivative of F is 2x.
We can take for example F(x)=x squared.
When you take the derivative of F,
you get 2x.
Be careful, there isn't unicity
of the primitive F:
it's enough to add some constant C to F
to get another primitive of f.
Indeed if you derivate x squared + C
the constant +C vanishes when you derivate.
An other example:
the function g(x) = 2/x
The constant 2 can be set aside.
What is, when you take the derivative,
gives us 1/x?
We know the result has the form ln.
ln(x) but you have to add the constant 2,
in front of ln(x).
When you take the derivative of 2 ln(x),
you get 2/x.
Do not forget the constant C.
We're changing the variable
There is a constant 3, we ca set aside.
What is, when you take the derivative,
gives us 1/t squared?
The result is - 1/t.
-1/t with the constant 3 here,
plus C.
A last example:
what is, when you take the derivative,
gives us exp?
A exp always gives us exp too
with a constant you have to determine in front of it.
Therefore exp of t/2 becomes exp of t/2
(it doesn't change)
But imagine I did'nt put the 2 here,
if you derivate exp of t/2,
you actually derivate a function like exp of u,
and because the derivative of exp u
is u' times exp u,
the u' here is 1/2.
But there is no 1/2 and then
you have to multiply the primitive by 2.
And we add the constant C.
How to apply these computation of primitives
to computation of integrals?
This is given by the fundamental analys theorem,
which relies integral with primitive.
To compute this integral,
we can find a primitive
of the function x times exp of x^2.
This function over here
has actually the form
exp of u where u is x squared
and in front of the exp
is almost u' (up to a constant 2).
We have x,
nevertheless it doesn't matter:
up to a constant we could have 2x.
This function has then the form:
u' times exp(u).
We know a primitive of u' times exp(u)
It is exp(u)
up to a constant 1/2
(because 2 is missing).
This integral equals bracket
of some primitive we've found 1/2 exp x^2
(without any constant).
This bracket is taken between 0 and 2,
which are the two limits of the integral respectively.
The bracket means:
we can develop it
into the function taken at
the upper bound of the bracket, that is 2
minus the same function
taken at the lower bound of the bracket, 0.
We simplify theses quantities,
and we get
One half times exp of 4 minus one half.
This integral, namely the area
below the graph of this function between 0 and 2,
equals this value.
A second example.
We need to compute a primitive
of ln of x over x.
First, it isn't necessarly obvious,
but we can rewrite this integral
separating the quotient to a product:
1/x times ln(x).
If you set u equals ln(x),
it turns out that 1/x is exactly u'.
Then the function has the form u' times u.
And u' times u has a well-known primitive.
It is u squared
with 1/2 in front of it.
(because the derivative of u squared is 2u times u')
Here 2 is missing,
so you have to add 1/2 to get the right value.
So the derivative of ln(x) squared over 2
is precisely the function over here.
And we need to develop the bracket:
we begin with the upper bound,
ln of e squared minus
the function taken at the lower bound 1.
We know that ln of 1 is zero
and ln of e is 1
So the value of the integral
is 1/2.